No phone calls on stage here.
Um, first off, was that cool or what?
What do you guys think? Huh?
>> Yeah.
>> Huge congratulations to Paw, Jacob, the
teams at Microsoft and Nvidia. Um, I
will say they were kind enough to send
me a Surface Laptop Ultra for the last
few days. It is amazing, but I think I
won the workstation for Christmas. Now,
now there's a bunch of stuff about the
exciting future to get into, but before
we do that, I was looking both of you up
last night on YouTube, and it's quite
rare to see both of these gentlemen on
stage together, and I was thinking about
how, you know, you both had a history,
these two great companies had a history
going back decades. You both
individually had histories of working
with each other going back decades. Ties
to me. My first job was at Microsoft. my
first paycheck a GeForce FX to play
Halfife 2. So, so maybe to start us off
and Jensen, what is your favorite memory
uh or fun memory of working with Satia
and Microsoft?
>> Well, uh Nvidia was founded because of
Windows. It was 1992, late '92, uh
Windows 3.1, and we were just started to
see the the vision of what a what a
personal computer really can be. And at
the time, frankly, we had never I'd
never even see a PC before. I largely
worked on workstations. We had, you
know, we had uh file servers and
supercomputers that we used to design
chips with. And and the founders and I,
you know, talked about this future where
maybe uh a personal computer with 3D
graphics would enable it to do things
like games and and be a workstation and
design things. And so we we imagine
about this world. If not for Windows, uh
Nvidia wouldn't have been founded. And
then and of course
and of course we we started in 1993
um uh Windows 95 really made reinvented
Windows 95.
>> Wow.
Am I on
>> Windows Windows 95
made possible the GPU to be connected to
uh uh a personal computer and what
revolutionized the GPU was DirectX.
Direct 3D uh was the API that really uh
enabled us to re uh reveal the
capabilities of GPUs into applications.
But then DX8 came along and we
co-invented with Microsoft the world's
first G programmable GPU which is
programmable shaders which a few steps
later evolved into uh CUDA as we know it
>> and so if you look at the entire journey
of our company Windows was at the core
of it and if not for Windows there would
be no GeForce if no GeForce CUDA
wouldn't come to the world uh without
CUDA Alex Kresevki and Ilia Suscover um
Yan Lun, you know, uh Andrew Ang, none
of them would have uh found a computer
uh to do deep learning.
>> And here we are.
>> And is now going to do a little transfer
of market cap back to me.
>> I do that every day.
>> But it's extraordinary that journey uh
that Jensen recounted. I mean, it's kind
of the the it's the history of computing
in some sense. Um, and the thing, one of
the things, uh, that Jensen sort of
sparked for me was
he has been perhaps the most consistent
with the vision of what accelerated
computing can be. And this going back to
the trajectory, you've been the one
person in our industry who has had this
one idea whose sort of trajectory has
been the most expansive quite frankly
more so than even any single PC form
factor or chip architecture. Because I
look back, one of my first memories was
we were talking about essentially saying
in the cloud, how big can be accelerated
computing or high performance computing,
right? The first deal I remember was in
Azure, how do we make HPC a bigger
thing? Um and by the way if
>> Satia was the first user of Infiniban
inside a cloud which brought the first
supercomputer to open AI which boom
>> that's right if we had not done that
like the fascinating you know like life
is full of accidents but if we had not
done that for HPC
>> we wouldn't have had the supercomputer
to give to open AAI to go train a GPT
model and rest would have been history I
mean it was kind of one of those happen
stance that we had done the HPC see
stuff when we were building an
infinibandbased supercomputer and and
comes Sam and says hey do you have
computing and we said yeah maybe and and
so it's sort of like but the thing that
I really give Jensen all the credit
quite frankly is that consistency of
vision of what this can be not today not
tomorrow but as a secular trend and
that's kind of what you know brings us
even into this moment
>> and then it led to a conversation. It
led to a conversation I remember quite
well where Satia and I were talking
about so so what does this mean to the
PC? How do we make uh the the perfect PC
in the post era of all of this stuff and
you know of course the personal computer
is the ultimate tool. It's my ultimate
tool and for a whole generation of
people it's our ultimate tool. Um, what
happens in the era of agents, uh, when
when when the agent is on your computer,
it is now your personal assistant, but
it wants to have access to all of the
amazing tools that we have, but the
amazing tools are spread out in the
NVIDIA ecosystem into uh gaming PCs.
>> Yeah.
>> Into workstations. And that's where most
of the tools were, right? all the all
the all the do tools and all the
seammen's tools and uh autodesk and
adobe and you saw many of them just now
and you know we want the world's best
blender the world's best unreal the
world's best omniverse the world's best
katilla everything all sitting on the
same PC
>> um as the AI
>> and so how do we go create that by the
way took four years
>> wow
>> that was a four year ago conversation
and just incredible
>> now that's very a good segue here today
and Satia. So I think the last few
months you know we've been sort of
inundated with these stories of agents
and security you know we all use agents
I'm sure everybody here is using a muse
or uh instinct and you are giving full
disk access and you having it act as you
and today when you guys showed MXC it
seemed to me like a fundamental new
operating system primitive for agents
which is a break from where we have
been. So maybe talk to us about why the
OS is the right place for this and what
this primitive if you will opens up.
>> Yeah. No, first of all remember this all
started with coding agents all running
on the desktop. I mean in fact if you
sort of look at uh where is the agent
that needs this security primitive the
most? It's the local harness and its
access to the file system and to be able
to take action. And so that's why in
fact you know working with Jensen and
team we said look how do we wire you
know wire this in into the primitives
whether it's in the cloud or in uh uh in
the operating system locally and given
the fact that essentially coding went
there first where the harness is local
even if you were using a cloud model we
needed to make the desktop uh the most
secure place for agents to execute and
so that's where MXC comes from it's
fantastic to see open shell now fully
integrated and native with MXC the
controls that Pavin talked about right
which is containment itself has to be
done at every level right it's not about
sort of doing one thing and leaving the
other right it has to be at the microVM
it has to be at the WM it has to be at
the session the piece that I'm most
excited about is the Windows session
having containment right it's so so
critical then okay containment is
wonderful but then I need full
observability how do you get
observability you get it If you have an
identity for an agent that I can track I
can then see the entire exhaust of the
agent right all of it uh and then I can
govern it that means I can like classic
set policy and have it govern that is
now what's going to give peace of mind
whether it's to IT ops to sec ops uh and
by the way and the other thing that we
should also not forget is the ability to
track the token spend right and where
it's happening and so that's the
entirety of what we have tried to bring
together. It's not about any one thing.
It's about stitching all these things.
Having seen all these adoption cycles,
whether it's the consumer adoption
cycle, the enterprise adoption cycle, I
would say the thing that blocks broad
diffusion is not having that complete
thought on what is required. Right? So
if you do one and leave the other,
there's no trust and what have you. So I
feel very very good that we have brought
it together in the cloud in the in the
client across it sack and fin and it's
heterogeneous right it's not about any
one piece of Microsoft technology it's
about supporting it all
>> what Satia just said what Satia just
said uh is going to be the foundation of
the next generation of it as we know it
yeah if you go the words he used what he
described the architecture deeply
profound for the next generation of
computers just as Windows Windows and
and DirectX revolutionized how
applications were built.
>> MXC
is going to revolutionize how agents are
built and deployed
>> without it
started without it complete non-starter
and so this big big deal.
>> Now this is I think closely tied to the
next piece um for both of you which is
hybrid intelligence. Now this feels a
little different. I think everybody here
has uses large model in the cloud. You
use it, it runs a tool maybe using
Blender and you get back a response. We
all used that for the last in a few
years. This feels different where you
have a choice of models, some running
locally, some in the cloud, you're going
back and forth. And one sentence from
the presenter who spoke at GitHub, which
really stood out to me was you're
getting these tokens for free, right?
And so maybe talk to us about what this
opens up because this feels again
something new where you are running part
of the workload here in the locally on
your on your laptop part of it in the
cloud and intelligently routing between.
What does this open up?
>> Yeah. So first of all, you know, I think
this is one of those moments where
um some of the things that you've been
using all click together, right? In
fact, it's kind of I was thinking about
this in the late 80s when I was in grad
school. I kind of had a a terminal,
right? My VT0000 and a VAX. Um and um
and then I had a PC at home.
>> Um and I kind of was using it all. In
fact, it's interesting that on my PC, I
had um essentially a modem with a
terminal connecting to my wax and then I
had all my local DOSs and uh you know
early Windows and what have you and then
suddenly it took all and by the way I
had Usenet all of that stuff but except
it took all the way maybe until 95 and
even Mosaic right the first browser to
bring it all together as one seamless
experience right it's not about local
cloud, what have you. I just want to use
my computing power wherever it is in
sort of a seamless flow of what I'm
trying to get done. So when I was seeing
even what Danielle was showing that demo
is mind-blowing. I mean, think about
that moment. I think we're going to come
back years from now and say, "Oh my god,
that was when we saw
>> what he did was he went to Comfy UI. He
brought down a bunch of models, built a
bunch of assets, took it to Blender, uh
used that to even enhance those assets,
then used again brought it back to
Comfy. Oh, went to Photoshop, used a
local model perhaps to sort of enhance
it, took it back to Comfy UI, then took
it all to the cloud with Astra, with
Unreal, but he just used apps on his
desktop, models, local, models in the
cloud. It all just worked. That is what
this is about. Like that's kind of where
today was about multiple fantastic
devices, all these things. But the
trajectory for me is so clear. There
will never be a moment where we will go
and look and say, "Oh, this runs
locally, this runs in the cloud." You
will expect this hybrid intelligence to
be everywhere and pervasive. And I think
that that's what to me is pretty
exciting. Yeah, that one application
what you just said Blender was
accelerated, Comfy UI was accelerated,
Astro was in the cloud, the agents were
locally. I mean, it's just the the
surface area surface area. That's cool.
The surface area of computing was
magnificent.
>> Yeah,
>> it is comp. It it brought together
literally the entire might of lit every
single technology company in human
history came together for that one
application.
>> That's right. And and by the way going
back to sort of the way you talk about
accelerated computer that was I mean his
point about why he was excited what took
him multiple days takes him hours like
that the fact that he was accelerated in
his ambition
>> and that to me is pretty cool which I
think you know this ties closely to
something else because these models have
gotten very good at tool use but the
tools often live locally. you know the
files live locally. By the way, you
know, Jacob and I are still both of us
are filing taxes at the last minute
apparently. Um and and I think there is
a aspect here about
>> I want my data to be secure and safe and
control. I want the tool use to happen
near where the data is where if you look
at what Jacob showed at co-pilot like
that it really opens up something new.
>> Yeah. I mean to me like one of the
things right if you look at it in fact
one of the when the coding agents became
the thing I was excited to see everybody
was in love with you know one the
console uh and everybody was love with
file systems again it just shows how
powerful of an abstraction a file system
is I think agents are going to be the
largest users of file system they need
to be secure
>> they need to be because they're a
heterogeneous collection space uh and
what His tax example, Jacob SP, it was a
great one, right? Basically, what it did
was it organized from, as he said, from
downloads, from even cloud files, email,
everything into a file system container
and then used models locally and in the
cloud to go do stuff with it.
>> And that is the new computer, right? So,
it's a I use the computer, my agents use
the computer, the agents need these
primitives as well. And so I think like
one drive when was the last time I
thought of one drive as a cloud thing or
as a client thing it's there everywhere.
Yeah. And so to me that is what I think
we are beginning to see is hey I want my
primitives for my agents to use 24 by7.
The form factor when I'm using it on my
PC should feel like I'm using it on my
PC. When I'm roaming it should roam with
me. You know what's amazing as you know
is is that these agents are going to be
better users of tools than us. And the
reason for that is just we know 10 15%
of the features of any application but
the agent knows every single feature.
>> That's right.
>> And so so the the the fact that the
tools these incredible tools are sitting
on your PC. They're they're accelerated
in in this incredible computer Surface
Ultra. Uh now the agent has access to
all of that capability. Who knows what
we're going to be able to do. I mean
just look at what it did. was the
Blender, the Unreal, the Comfy AI was
incredible.
>> Can of show of hands, how many people
here have tried using one of these apps
locally with the model in the last
couple of months or a few months? Great.
Right. And so I think this just kind of
show goes to show where you can actually
bring the tools locally. Now Jensen, I
want to ask you about the hardware piece
of this, right? We very often see you
talking about these big massive you know
Vera Rubins Blackwells NVL72s
you know these you know intelligence
token factories um you know that's you
know that power data centers here today
we're talking about something different
right like we're talking about the spark
the workstation which I really want for
Christmas you know which runs in your
office talk to me a little bit about how
you see this evolution about tokens
being produced like right next to you as
opposed to you know Ver Rub in data in
the data center.
>> Well uh the number of engineers that
worked on this project is incredible
over 4,000 engineering years. This is a
massive project. I mean look what we've
done. We've reinvented the personal
computer completely. For the first time
we took all the capabilities what used
to be in a gaming PC, in a laptop uh in
a workstation in a supercomput in the
cloud. We unified the architecture and
we made it run on one super chip. This
super chip, you know, it's rectangular
because it's two giant chips fused
together. And so this it's a beast. It
has one pedlops. Just to put in
perspective, the computer that started
the AI revolution called DGX1 was one
pedal
>> and it was a quarter of a bill it was a
quarter of a billion dollars and um it
weighed 500 pounds and now it's in this
in your laptop. Um, but what's what's
amazing is this is also the only
computer the only computer in the world
that runs DirectX and all of its
applications OpenGL and every single
version of it because we need all of the
tools and design tools, right? Creative
tools. We need everything to run. We
need Unreal to run incredibly well. So,
DirectX has to be amazing and it runs
every single CUDA application
incredibly. what what uh Satia and I
were talking about four years ago is,
you know, we're going to have a whole
new generation of software developers
and these software developers are going
to be AI software developers. They're
either going to be creating AI
applications and AI models or they're
going to be using AI to to develop their
software. And so the computer has to be
revolutionized and has to be really good
at CUDA from the ground up. And so this
is the only computer on the planet that
runs everything natively on the device.
the first time ever. And so it took
thousands of us to do this, but it also
took the entire industry. Look behind
us. Every single laptop maker, every
single do desktop maker, every single
workstation maker joined us.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow.
>> This is the first time I think first
time I think a new piece of hardware, a
new computer architecture have come
together and the entire industry top to
bottom, left to right, everybody's
involved, every single geography. And so
this is a complete reinvention. We
understand the seriousness of the work
that we're doing doing here. We've now
test tested some over,200
applications, the most intense
applications in the world. All fully
tested, performance tested,
compatibility tested, everything has
been optimized. We're going to keep on
going. The support for this system, the
the amount of software we're going to
bring to it, middleware, algorithms, I
mean, it will never end. This is just a
magnificent thing that when you when you
finally look at it, you look at this
beautiful laptop. Pav stands up here
with this beautiful laptop, you know,
but the number of engineers between our
two companies and all of the companies
around the world that did this
incredible all because we believe that
the personal computer was our tool tool
for people. Now it's going to be tool
for people, but it's also going to be
our personal assistant that uses the
tool.
>> Now, one last thing for both of you. I
think if you've been on X for the last
few days, there has been this intense
conversation about I would say personal
agents. We've been talking about
productivity and maybe enterprise agents
here, whether it is Muse, Instinct,
there's this question about, hey, when
this agent goes out and makes a
purchase, is that me or the agent? Who
is liable for it? And if I'm a service
provider, how do I react to this human
being no longer showing up on my
website? And people are trying to build
standards. And as an industry, I think
we're trying to figure this out. So I'm
sort of curious if you kind of had to
peer on the crystal ball a bit. Where do
you see this headed? Right? Is it
standards? Is it the industry coallesing
around some new behaviors? Where do you
see this headed?
>> Yeah, I mean first of all I think it
starts with a little bit of the
conversation we had uh in the early part
which is trust. Um and trust starts with
things like hey are these agents
contained? Do they have identity? is the
exhaust uh of the agent with the
identity separate from the user right
which is one of Pawan's thing was how do
we make sure the agent ID that's even
working on behalf is separate from the
user and you need it even for everyday
uh usage but you also need it for what I
think you're referencing which is how do
I then trust what do I delegate in fact
if you look at the first decision that
we are making is what is my delegation
um you know authority that I'm giving to
the agent uh on my behalf of right and
that is a decision that's going to be
based on trust and it'll keep increasing
the more autonomous it is uh you trust
it and go so then I think on the
consumer space this will come down to
even you know I I think of it as
insurance will price this
>> insurance
>> because at some level we can all talk
about it's not like oath is hard to do
right I think the protocols are good we
should do them and tag But ultimately
it's going to be pricing the the
essentially the agent working on my
behalf. Uh and how does the marketplace
price it?
>> Your question at the at the foundation
of it. MXC is so foundational. Open
Shell the work that we're doing
together. It's about it's about trust.
It's about containment. It's about
observability monitoring. If we can't
get that right
>> That's right. Oh yeah.
>> If we just can't get right. So that's
the first part. We have got to secure
that part of it so that the agents that
are operating on our behalf, doing
things on our behalf, we give it minimum
rights. It has credentials. It is
monitored and trusted. Only then can we
allow these agents to really go off and
do do uh do tasks on our behalf.
>> You know, today's a powerful moment. I
remember when open clock came out from
there with the terminal hacking to get
their own um gateway to here where it is
an embedded piece of Windows, you know,
with tokens running accelerated. It's
quite something.
>> So much engineering went engineering
went into that the ride today.
>> Amazing. And it is a great device. Let
me just tell you that honestly. Well,
Jensen Satia, thank you so much. It's a
great day. Thank you for having me. And
I'm going to throw it back to Pavin
>> and Satia
Microsoft team. We have reinvented the
computer as we know it.
>> Thank you so much, Jensen. Thanks for
the partnership. Really excited today.
And I think as you said like one thing I
if I can end with Jensen just in passing
talked about the vision for this was how
do we I mean Windows has always been
about how do we not leave any piece of
code any piece of framework behind and
bring it all. The fact that he talked
about hey we're going to bring all of
Windows apps all of the the graphics
apps all of CUDA all of OpenGL and now
with the token factory that is what is
mind-blowing. Windows has been with me
for 34 years. Looks like it's going to
be with me for 34 more.
>> There you go. Thank you so much.